The
Speaker 1: gentleman from Kentucky, Mr. Massey is recognized for five minutes.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Mr. Dolio, my colleague, Mr. Crawford, asked you about flexibility in the airport improvement program, which are federal dollars that come back to the airports, and you lamented the fact that there was a shortage in revenue, that flexibility would help in that program,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): needed more funds. Can you talk about the other sources of revenue that airports have and how that plays into it? Particularly, my follow-up question is going to be about the passenger facility charge.
Good.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Okay. The airports have different funding sources to use for capital projects. Of course, PFC program, the AIP grant program,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): airport funds that remain and are usable after all expenses are taken care of, are pretty much the bigger pots. Right now we have the temporary bill program that will run for another three years. Now, you heard the stats earlier that there's $30 billion a year need in airport infrastructure development.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Those funds combined over airports, the AIP program, PFCs, airport revenues, equate to about $13 billion a year, so there's still a big gap, so something has to give or something has to be done to start closing that gap.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): The PFC program, when it was stood up in 2000 at $3 and later, I'm sorry, in 90 at $3 and 10 years later was bumped to $450, has lost value over time with inflation. So it doesn't buy you the same thing it did then. Bumping the PFC would be a very significant help.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and it would be airports self-generating the funds from local users of airports and airport facilities. So it's a big gap, and again, the flexibility would help, but really we need to bump the programs and provide more funding.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Sometimes when Congress wants to raise taxes, we call it a user fee as a euphemism.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): But the passenger facility charge never goes into our coffers here at the federal government. It truly is a user fee because it goes from the user to the airport. Can you talk about how you use those fees responsibly and what you would do if we did increase the cap?
Speaker 4: for the first time in many years, allowing you to collect your own revenue? It's with the big infrastructure needs, a lot of
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): it in terminals and land side. What the PFC program does is gives you the flexibility to use those funds in those areas as opposed to everything on the year field. The AIP program
is
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): more geared to airfield improvement. So as PFC revenues increase, airports have a better ability to improve terminals, improve the airfield as well. We can use those funds on the airfield. They can provide matches to grants that we receive in picking up that gap. And the more we can do with grants and with the PFC program,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): It's less we have to do with debt and less costs that flow down to the air carriers that fly in and out of our facilities. So we're always, as airport operators, we are consistently looking for ways to find our needs. And no one's -- and I can tell you, I've been the CEO in three airports. The needs were different in each, and we adapt to the needs. New Orleans, the new terminal was essential.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): In St. Louis, we went through a significant upgrade of the existing facilities, and that was sufficient there. In San Antonio, a new terminal and concourse was needed to replace a World War II facility.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): It's different needs everywhere. None of us are out building monuments to our greatness. It's just essential needs in those communities. The PFC program has gone a long
Speaker 5: way in helping us develop those facilities, but it is losing value with inflation. I'm
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): sorry I don't have much time, Mr. Santa, but I had a question for you and hopefully the chairman will indulge me and allow you to answer it if I go over time. We've seen recent
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): reports, and I don't know if they're true or apocryphal, or if these are things that happened in the past and we just didn't pay attention, but we've seen recent reports of, I don't know how you characterize them, but I'll call them near misses, when planes are taking off and landing and get closer than we're comfortable with at airports. I've seen those in social media. I don't know if it's more than normal. Can you let the public know, are those
reports
Speaker 6: There are an increased number of those incidents, and if so, what do you think the cause is?
Well, some
Speaker 7: of the recent events that have been in the news are, you know, they're troubling for us. It's an increased amount of risk that we're unwilling
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): to accept right now, but they really are inspired and invoked, unfortunately, by
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): uh lack of staffing when you control more traffic with less operational positions you introduce risk into the system now the ntsb is is uh investigating those we partner with him we're part of the uh the investigation to ensure that we learn from those uh events and we don't repeat those but ultimately working more traffic six-day work weeks 10-hour days introduced introduces risks to the system thank
you
Speaker 9: mr chairman i yield back
uh ranking member the
Speaker 9: focus